a
[Music]
w
hello everybody and welcome back to the
223rd episode of the asket show hope
everyone is doing great thank you so
much for being on this live stream with
me this nice evening this this nice Day
morning wherever you are and uh I'm
going to take questions both from the
comments and from the live chat it's
going to be a mix of both but I've
selected a bunch of questions from the
comments and I'll also take questions
from the live chat so before we do that
let me see who all is there on the live
stream let me let me greet some of you I
can see J manraj Singh Ashish pandel Vin
Paul Gil jatin Kumar bhan manindra Chri
gorav rati Ray Raj Singh amay T ranki ym
anant Pai Anish somya dat om prash toit
Jan feminist Slayer Kip Chan Zub eang
hello karat
Jam uh geopolitical du hello Akash Barat
first Sam tripati abishek Sida says J
Lord r rwi majumdar Super Rex udip DEA
swapn daso sha threat Ripper hello just
manra Singh again rajat Duhan VII man
hello
anandu n jiger bind Vikram geopolitical
geopolitical dub hello
shiv shagun Chopra hello Adian Rajan ym
goami um maheswari Baba abijit CH xas
Yus Zas Zas Alvin Rodriguez Shin
Goda par SSM Joy mukarji Akay Kanna sair
29 janavi jayhind J Paul VI Med Shri
Chan sham Shaman ra seven truth and so
many other people so I'm not going to be
able to greet everybody but thank you so
much for being here Anita gav
Haz and everybody else okay so let's get
going with the questions I'll take some
questions from the comments that you've
asked the comments first and then I'll
take questions alternating perhaps from
live chat and comments and that's how we
will take it but before we do that let
me remind you all of the uh
of the abijit Chaat Clips channel in
case you seek answers to individual
questions this is this here is the
channel that you need to look at
hopefully subscribe if if it makes sense
to you U I'm uploading individual uh
answers to questions uh questions to
individual answers on this channel uh
and you can find uh you know questions
that have been asked in recent live
streams and the answers over here on
this channel the link is in the live
chat the link is also in the description
please go ahead and subscribe to it if
this is something that makes sense to
you thank you very much and before I
begin I would like to uh once again
thank ramal lakmi Viv for the incredible
work he's doing every time I do a live
stream he always invariably puts up the
time stamps it helps everybody so much
it helps me it helps all the viewers who
want to check out individual answers so
once again ramal lakmi I I cannot thank
you enough for the incredible work work
you're doing I really really appreciate
it and I'm very grateful to you thank
you very much ramal
lakmi okay let's uh let's take some
questions what's question what's the
first question okay it's by a couple of
people uh why is the Russian Chess
Federation why has why have they accused
China's ding Len of losing the world
championship intentionally in
questioning the why they question the
legitimacy of of dues we should
celebrate a gk's win and what's with so
many Russian players just players being
salty to gesh Vladimir
kramnik Ian NE nepo I can't pronounce
the name nepo uh the president of the
Chess Federation of Russia what's going
on I don't think it's a Russian issue
okay it's not just the Russians who are
doing it uh India is this up and
cominging Nation historic I mean we are
the inventors of Chess as a civilization
thousands of years ago but historically
the past Century and a century or so we
have not really had too many chess
champions
if we if we go to Google and we let's
say uh try and search for the list of
Chess Champions let's let's quickly do
that okay let's go to Google list of
Chess World Champions let's let's do
that let's go to chess.com
and here we have the list so how many
Indians we we had Anand from 2007 to
2013 he was he's a four time previous
four time past world champion before
that we had so many others and no
Indians you know some real greats we had
Alexander Alin mik binik the great
karpov the great Kasparov we had
Vladimir
kramnik uh and and recently Magnus
Carlson and now dingl and now finally
gkes domaru so India is this upand
cominging nation no real history in the
in the recent past of of any great feats
when it comes to
chess and now we have this guy this
young 18-year-old kid essenti who has
won the Chess Championship and how did
he win it I
mean this guy the the defending Champion
Ling Duran he blundered at the very end
by you know positioning his rook in the
wrong place which led to a rook exchange
uh the bishop his Bishop was trapped
that went off and then it was just end
game you know uh and and he and ding had
to resign after that so it was a
terrible blunder but let's understand
that these PE these chess players the
grand Masters who are playing at the
very highest level are under incredible
stress when they are playing uh they
spent insane amounts of time preparing
for everything and this was the final
game of the Chess Championship 6.5 6.5
and there was a tremendous amount of
pressure on both players and at that
stage it's all about mental toughness
both are equally good but it's all about
it it all balls down to mental toughness
and clearly gukesh was tougher I mean he
was the match was Meandering towards a
draw but gesh kept on playing he did not
offer offer a draw he kept on playing he
just grounded out and he waited for the
opponent to crumble under pressure and
that's what happened so it's not an
intentional def intentional loss by
dingl I mean come on he's a great
Champion himself one of the great
players that we have today you can't
without any evidence accus him of
intentionally losing what will he gain
by doing that what will he gain by doing
that by by losing intentionally that's
nonsense it's just that some people uh
are jealous they're unhappy with with
the way the the that India is rising in
the world there is there could be an
amount of racism I mean Magnus Carlson
the previous Champion he has been rather
uncharitable towards gkes and and kind
of uh not not
said things that are not very very nice
about gesh he has been like that he's
not been a very gracious former Champion
rather rude and all so it's not just the
Russians it's a lot of people who who
are doing that and what can I say we in
India need we we obviously we should
celebrate the great victory of
gukesh 18 years old the youngest ever
World chess champion and above and ahead
of him came G so many greats the names
of Kasparov karpov vishwanathan Anand M
binik Bobby Fisher I mean some of the
greatest of all time and he is now one
of them I think he had posters on his
walls of these people and now he is one
of them that's what he has achieved so
incredible Victory by gukesh
congratulations to gukesh obviously the
whole nation 1.4 billion people most of
them are celebrating along with you and
lots of people are happy about about
this across the world that's so always
going to be some some of some people who
are not happy ignore them and if they
have a problem with this what what can I
say
cope all
right okay next question what's the next
question okay this thing is blowing up
now so ainka says I'm currently residing
in New Jersey that's in on the on the
east coast in the US uh it's very close
to New York and there have been numerous
reports of large drone or unidentified
flying objects UFOs in the area
government officials in the FBI have
stated that they are unsure of what
these things are what are these things
we have no idea that's what they say it
seems remarkable that a nation with such
Advanced
capabilities might not be able to
identify activity within its own
airspace I would appreciate your
perspective on this matter and the
second question is is the US government
deliberately hiding info about the
recent UFO sightings or could these
sightings be linked to Advanced human
technology or the aliens oh my God
what's going on is the question
now uh PE viewers who know me for a
while for for for a couple of years
maybe more they would be aware that I
have historically been a very strong UFO
skeptic I have disappointed many
podcaster podcast hosts and and
interviewers by saying that I am
extremely skeptical about the UF UFO
phenomenon I am not convinced that
aliens are visiting us I'm not convinced
that these phenomena are real I have not
seen any evidence that convinces me that
that makes me change my mind that's what
I have said over and over again to the
disappointment of many people lots of
people but now the evidence is out there
no question about it so what is this
evidence I mean this evidence is out
there now you cannot question the fact
that this phenomenon exists news
stations have reported this
live it's been caught initially a few
weeks ago live on on a random newscast I
mean there are there's a panel of of
people you know news anchor sitting on a
around a desk and discussing something
in the background there's a night view
of the city which is live and you see
UFO flying around on that you can't deny
that and then there are there are news
stations that have set up um uh cameras
with high powered uh lenses on tripods
and they've captured very detailed views
of of these phenomena of these objects
and there's a
whole multitude of different kinds of
objects that we have witnessing so
there's no question anymore that these
phenomena
exist okay now are these the same
phenomena that people were speaking
about in the 19 1900s we're not sure
about that because see what's happening
is that we are now living currently in
the Drone era and there is the obvious
difficulty that we're going to face
of
discriminating and differentiating
between genuine UFO phenomena and
unusual or unidentified drones that look
like
UFOs now everybody has a drone I mean
not everybody but every content creator
has a
drone lots of amateurs have drones
people just for hobby purposes have
drones and you can and and companies
have drones the military has drones
there are drones that we are not aware
of drone types
uh there are drones that are military
drones and Commercial drones that come
in various sizes and shapes and all that
50 kilogram drones 100 kilogram 200
kilogram 500 kilogram drones with all
kinds of characteristics so are these
just drones you know he create drones so
that's what we are grappling with but
what's clear is that some of these
cannot be drones because they're
emerging out of the ocean or flying
above the ocean where there's no land
nearby like hundreds of kilometers
around there's no land but you see these
objects there and some some of these
seem to be dipping into the ocean or
emerging from the ocean which is very
weird uh there are drones that are
hovering around there are UFOs that are
hovering around uh military
bases and that's weird and and
anti-drone technology that normally
works against these drones which which
can bring the drones down doesn't work
here if if and there's been this
incident that a person tried to launch
his own drone to take to to get a closer
view at a UFO and that drone just
immediately run out of
battery and there have been UFOs that
are hovering over that are landing at
Power stations and apparently draining
power all kinds of weird phenomena are
happening and I've seen time lapses of
hundreds of UFOs over New Jersey so
something is happening it looks like
there's a UFO or UAP or whatever you
want to call it invasion of New Jersey
of the US and and there are other
nations that have reported these
phenomena the UK has reported lots of
these phenomena China have seen some
videos Argentina and where not I think
in India we need to look up at the sky
you know in India in metropolitan cities
people just look down they never look up
look up and you may find something so
that's the thing so now the question is
what's
happening let's let's analyze the
possibilities logically what what could
actually be happening so um like I said
there could be two types of aircraft one
could be just drones secret drones
secret uh designs of drones that we not
aware of but these are just human-made
drones high technology drones that's one
possibility the second possibility is
actual
UFOs okay which are nonhuman apparently
these are the two possibilities now
let's go dive deeper into this so there
have been you know spec there's been
speculation on social media on Twitter
Etc that uh what we are witnessing on
New Jersey which is going over the
Atlantic Ocean and all that is that we
actually these are actually military
drones
uh that are searching for apparently
radioactive material so maybe the these
are very large drones that have
detectors you know germanian High Purity
germanian detectors that are looking for
and these detectors they can typically
detect uh Jamar Ray which is something
that uh radioactive materials dangerous
materials emit now I'm not sure what the
range of these hpge detectors is but
apparently some people are claiming or
speculating that these are military
drones that are searching for uh lose
nuclear material or illicit nuclear
material in the New York area maybe
that's been smuggled in perhaps pure
speculation but maybe it's been smuggled
in as they that's what they claim to
make dirty bombs or something so that's
one possibility so maybe it's a US
government that has Unleashed its Army
of futuristic secret drones to to search
for uh lose nuclear material that maybe
terrorists or Smugglers have brought
into the us maybe that's that okay
that's one possibility the other
possibility is that these are
anti-missile defense systems secret
anti-missile defense systems mounted on
drones perhaps and they have been
perhaps deployed as a message to the
Russians after Putin recently tested a
Hypersonic ballistic missile uh what is
oresnik or something which is reportedly
able to capable of defeating NATO
defenses so that's another piece of
speculation that maybe these are you
know futuristic secret anti-missile
defense systems that doesn't make a lot
of sense but I'm just saying what people
are
speculating maybe these are secret US
government uh weapons platforms military
weapons platforms being tested for
deployment but then why do it why not do
it over the desert in Nevada area 51 or
wherever why do it over New Jersey
doesn't make sense
right maybe they just trying to scare
the people you know maybe they want uh
the US Congress to to pass very strict
new drone restrictions that will
prohibit citizens from from flying
drones at will so maybe that's why they
have Unleashed this UFO Invasion makes
no sense but that's the kind of
speculation we seeing then there's
speculation that this could be a fake
Alien
Invasion which is being done by the
people who control the world apparently
you create a problem you elicit a
reaction and then you propose a solution
then you implement a solution so you you
create a fake Alien Invasion you first
have these D drone swarms going around
UFO swarms going around New Jersey and
where not then you make it look like
there's an actual Alien Invasion
happening then you the reaction you will
get is panic among the people of Earth
and then you propose a new solution a
One World Government so this is a just
pure speculation that we are seeing on
the internet there's no evidence of this
but I mean logically it's plausible it
unlikely or whatever but it's
plausible now what could actually make
sense from my perspective is that this
is just extremely Advanced uh
technology uh developed by various uh us
defense uh defense manufacturers like
lockhead Martin or general atomic or
whoever whoever but then why would
they unleash it over the Skies of New
Jersey and other places why now and why
so many of them all over the place
not really sure why that would be the
case I I can't speculate and there's one
more piece of speculation which there's
no evidence of that uh these uh uaps
drones whatever they are alien
technology that's been reverse
engineered by the US so defense
manufacturers defense contractors like
loid Martin Etc they have not developed
all this technology from scratch but or
or from from what we know of theoretical
physics but they have reverse they have
covered and reverse engineered alien
technology exotic alien technology
that's another piece of speculation that
we have been hearing for quite some time
on the internet how far is it true we
don't know because we don't have any
evidence this way or the or the other
way so these are the various
possibilities what's the last
possibility real
aliens so these are the possibilities I
don't know what's happening look I don't
have access to the actual data and
evidence uh that would give us a
definitive answer in the absence of that
I can tell you what the speculations are
on the internet right now I've been
following this for for some time
now uh so logically some of these things
are very tenuous logically some of these
uh possibilities make a little more
sense uh the answer lies somewhere in
one of these possibilities or somewhere
in between that's what I can say and we
got to keep keep an eye on this because
this is now becoming a very very
prominent phenomenon it's interesting
that Elon Musk has not said anything
about this uh I believe the US
government had tried to
elude had tried to allege perhaps
indirectly that Iran was behind this
that Iran has is sending UFOs or ufs to
the US makes no sense makes no sense so
uh it's interesting that Elon Musk the
guy who owns SpaceX the most powerful
space Explorer on the planet currently
it's interesting that Elon Musk this guy
has not said a word about about these
phenomena very interesting it's also
interesting that Donald Trump has not
said much about this he recently put out
communicate communicate that uh there's
something going on and we need to get to
the bottom of this but that's just one
piece of uh communication that has put
out otherwise it's been very taciturn
about this particular matter so very
interesting we don't quite sure what's
happening so it could be the US
government that's behind this it could
be
uh US Government having recovered alien
technology and reverse engineered that
or it could be an actual Alien
Invasion I'm not sure what the answer is
but this
phenomenon is a genuine phenomenon now
no question about
it okay uh love from Pakistan well
greetings from
India uh and thank you for uh watching I
appreciate that so the question is is it
safe to find extra terrestrial life
their immune system and our immune
system will be different so is it risky
for the survival of
both both Us and Them and some risks you
know better than me discuss please what
hopefully could happen when we may
interact with each other look uh when it
comes to uh Alien
biology uh that's pure speculation we
have no
idea uh what alien biology could look
like what it could be like uh if we ever
encounter
aliens what sort of biological system
may they have could it be just like us
carbon based life forms could it be
silicon based life forms could it be
completely different form of life uh you
know we live in this goldilock Zone
around the Sun uh where liquid water can
flow but you could have life on Titan
which is the moon of Saturn where you
have temperatures that are below 200°
below minus 200 celius and you have
liquid hydrocarbons liquid methane and
all that you could have life that could
emerge out of that at extremely low
temperatures compared to what we are
accustomed to and we cannot even begin
to speculate about whether they have
immune systems or what they have and
what they may not have will there be DNA
based life forms that can only happen
with carbon based life forms so it's
it's entirely purely
speculative we can't even begin to uh
speculate what kind of life forms these
could be if we ever come across aliens
uh obviously uh they if aliens exist and
if they do ever come to Earth they'll be
coming from a different planet right and
therefore they would have take certain
precautions to ensure that they don't uh
that because they're this the conditions
they they accustomed to could be very
different from what we have on this
planet here so they would have takeen
certain precautions not to get exposed
to the elements here and that could kill
them perhaps and for us also we would
have to try and figure out what kind of
biology is it that we are dealing with
uh and is it harmful to us if if there
is contact between us and Aliens then
it's going to be a process of trial and
error for both sides maybe they are if
they if they do reach here they'll be
way technologically way more advanced
than us so it'll be easier for them it
will be much harder for
us uh what could happen when we interact
with each other hopefully they will come
in peace like they say but you can never
take that for granted so yeah if if if
there is contact between us and an alien
civilization it should trigger alarm
bells in every major capital of every
Sovereign Nation on the earth there
there are only four Sovereign Nations it
should trigger serious alarm Bells it
will be crisis time okay we can't assume
that they will come in peace
so that'll be a big crisis for us
yeah okay let's take a question or two
from
um from the live
chat okay let's take this question by
kiril Sor can India make another Union
another state or Union territory out of
Manipur as Manipur is protected by
UTI postis jurist I have no idea what
UTI POS UT POS jurist is I'm not sure
what that is it's it's obviously Latin
terminology judicial terminology uh I am
not an expert in law so I don't know
what that
is why would the question is can India
make another state or Union treaty out
of Manipur the question is why would we
want to do that there is a crisis in
Manipur right now right we know that the
crisis is very simple what is the
problem we have to Define it first the
problem is not that mes are asking for
St
status but that's not the problem the
problem is that there is a for an
invasion of foreigners who are now
squatting on Indian Territory in
Manipur that's what's happened illegal
aliens have infiltrated in the number of
lacks into India which is Manipur and
they are in occupation of a very
significant percentage of the territory
of the state of Manipur that is the
problem and the solution is to to that
is to evict all illegal infiltrators out
of India that's the solution why do we
need to make a union territory to uh to
make make the foreigners
happy foreigners have no right to even
one square centimeter of Indian
Territory let's be very clear about that
right so you can you can talk for hours
and days about the Manipur issue this
the problem is very very simple you can
make it as complicated as you want as
many so-called experts do they go into
man details and talk discussed that for
hours big picture the problem is very
simple illegal infiltration and
occupation of Indian Territory by
foreigners because of the open borders
policy that we've had since
1949 and you want to change that it's
going to take time but that's that's the
problem the solution is very simple get
rid of all the foreigners foreigners
have no right to to even one square ctim
of inan territory once that is done the
problem is gone then we can look forward
to the Future right so there's no
question of creating a new state or new
UN territory out of Manipur uh or
whatever get rid of the foreigners evi
them back to wherever they came from
it's if they are facing issues in their
home country that is their problem not
ours we have enough problems of our own
so
yeah uh gorov says I think Rohit Sharma
should retire now
uh look Cricket is very controversial
I've opined before for about cricket and
people I mean I've got very very very
harsh reactions on Twitter I've been
watching Cricket since what I since I
was a kid right not it's one of the
sports I follow um and right now we're
not doing too well in Australia Ro cha
hasn't performed well in the previous
test that we lost to the Australians
first of all he came back from wherever
he was but did the first Cardinal
mistake in sports is to never the
Cardinal Ro rule is never change never
Tinker with a winning combination we won
the first
match and then they got rid of two guys
who did not perform that well in the
match but they brought in a guy who's
well past his Prime look Rohit Sharma
has never been a great test player he's
been a tremend one of the greatest of
all time in Odis in t20s but test match
is not so great Ki at least performed in
the first match not in the second match
so now I think it's do or die for Rohit
Sharma we always look I know that people
in India have are in love with various
players the objective of sport is to win
I don't care if so and so guys is
playing for his records of for so he
want these many runs or these many
centuries or half centuries I don't care
about that I am not interested in
personal records absolutely not all I
win is that all I want is that India
should win and if you have to ditch one
of your greats and so be it you have to
be ruthless in these
matters the Australians have always been
like this they got rid of Dean Jones
when he was in his prime for whatever
reason they they retired steveo forcibly
when steo still wanted to play that's
how you do it you always have to focus
on the future you have to focus on
winning you to be
ruthless the nation is bigger than the
individual but in India we all worship
individuals I think Rohit Sharma should
retire retire I agree Ki should soon
retire if he doesn't perform well in
this series I think you can play the IPL
or whatever you can keep watching him
and enjoying his uh playing there but
not at the N National level we need to
invest in youngsters we have PL plenty
of youngsters who can do way better
than some players who are currently
playing so
yeah okay let's go back to
uh
to the comments questions from the
comments okay mck l69 says Bangladesh
removes the security clearance required
for pakistanis to get a Bangladeshi Visa
what's the strategy behind this there's
no strategy or such behind this okay
there is a Strate strategy behind this
but it's not a Bangladeshi strategy look
the Bangladesh government is a puppet
regime it's a dictatorship it's an
autocratic puppet regime that's been
installed by the Americans okay and as
such they are simply puppets of the US
Muhammad yunus is a puppet of the United
States uh foreign
establishment uh state
so uh Department of
State so the policy is very simple
Bangladesh now becomes East Pakistan it
will behave with India exactly the way
Pakistan behaves uh Pakistan as we know
historically sadly was indulging in
terrorism against India for decades all
funded and finan by the US make no
mistake about it you could see the same
happening with Bangladesh they may if
they can
start a similar policy with India they
they obviously conducting this Mass this
genocide this prgram against Hindus the
press the media is quiet mostly about it
not all the media not the entire media
but most of the media is quiet about
this the Western media media will never
report it they are oppressing the Hindus
the indigenous Hindus of Bangladesh the
real inhabitants of Bangladesh that's
happening and uh the relationship
between Bangladesh and India is going to
get worse over
time so the objective of the US state
department is to encircle India from all
sides there's Pakistan that's Pakistan
now you create East Pakistan that's
equally hostile and then you have this
cooki land for Christ project K that's
going on they're trying to carve out uh
de
facto separate nation Christian Nation
out of Manipur mizoram Etc there's the
whole situation in Myanmar going on the
US has its fingerprints everywhere no
question about it right so it's very
simple that when you have East Pakistan
West Pakistan who say who serve the same
purpose and the same function of of
destabilizing India in in a variety of
ways then they should work together
right so why should Bangladesh now have
visa restrictions or extra security
clearances for pakistanis it's the same
country essentially so that's why this
has happened
okay okay couple of questions about
Bangladesh again Anita and mclan say
please share your opinion about the
looming possibility of war between India
and Bangladesh and direct or indirect
involvement of Pakistan and China and
what could happen if East Pakistan
attacks India would we retaliate uh this
time Russia will not be at our Aid okay
is there a possibility of war between
India and Bangladesh absolutely not how
can you have a war between an elephant
and a butterfly or rather an elephant
and a mosquito you can't have a war
between an elephant and a mosquito right
the mosquito can be a nuisance for the
elephant the mosquito can come and keep
on biting the elephant and making the an
uncomfortable and maybe give him malaria
or Deni or whatever other illnesses
exist but there can be no war between
the elephant in the
mosquito and no disrespect intended to
any people in Bangladesh I'm sure there
are lots of good people there as well
but I'm just giving you a metaphorical
representation of what's happening so
you can't have a war between an elephant
and a mosquito there's no question
there's no possibility Bangladesh is
going to serve as a nuisance for India
as a troublemaker for India they're
gonna make they're going to
they will try and destabilize the the
geographical region of Eastern India and
India's Far East which is what we call
the Northeast right that's what that's
the role that Bangladesh will pay play
as a proxy of the US state
department uh could be could could there
be direct or indirect involvement of
Pakistan and China Pakistan certainly
because Pakistan is West Pakistan and
Bangladesh is now East Pakistan so yes
they will coordinate their strategies
and work together
both are extensions or or puppets or
vasal wasal of the US state department
so there's going to be cooperation
between Pakistan East and West Pakistan
or Pakistan and Bangladesh China not
very much I don't see China getting
involved too much in this because yeah
if you ask me two years ago three years
ago China was essentially the Big Daddy
of West Pakistan pakist West Pakistan
under Imran Khan was kind of a wasal of
China but then there was a coup in West
Pakistan nobody realized it Imran Khan
was oued and Shabah Sharif came to power
was put in power was put in the seat the
hot seat the cool cool seat and that's
essentially a US takeover of of Pakistan
and then you have another coup in
Bangladesh and Sh Kaz is outad and
another Pro us puppet comes to power so
you have Pro us puppets on both sides so
there's going to be cooperation between
the two Nations Pakistan is going to be
involved they will synergize and
cooperate China not very much Pak China
has lost control lost ownership was
salaj of Pakistan West Pakistan and
China had some cooperation going on with
with Bangladesh but uh now Bangladesh is
firmly in the camp of China's major
adversary or rival which is the United
States so uh you can't expect too much
involvement of China in Bangladesh now
um now the next question is what if East
Pakistan attacks India well it's going
to be like a mosquito trying to attack
elephant it won't end well for the
mosquito and we will not need Russia at
our side or whatever why do you need
Russia why does an elephant need another
elephant or a larger elephant to help
him against the
mosquito you understand doesn't work uh
so yeah there's no question there's no
chance of a war between India and
Bangladesh it would be suicidal for the
mosquito all right Pai Paul says Syria
now under Rebel control Rebel control do
you think the US might attempt a Ukraine
likee strategy from this region against
Russia in the future what exactly is
their primary interest here natural
resources geopolitical leverage or a
long-term containment strategy against
Russia okay that's the question uh okay
let's take a look at the map because
this is a map kind of thing this is a
map kind of question where's the map
here's the map let me find the map
where's the map okay let me put that on
the screen let's take a look at the map
the geography of the region and what's
going on here is the question
so so we're talking about Syria which is
if we go west from India we cross the
temporary Nation we come into Persia and
from Persia go westwards you have Iraq
and then you have Syria this is the
nation right and it's currently under
let's say rebel control the rebels are
one of the offshoots or one of the
rebranded uh configurations of al-Qaeda
Isis whatever okay former terrorists or
are still terrorists I mean the the guy
the AL
julani the head of the government is has
been declared by the us as a terrorist
in the past the Tweet still exists find
this terrorist or help us find this
terrorist but now he is on the good
books of the US in the good books of the
US he wears the same dress the same
costume that uh another actor wears
what's his name zalinsky same kind of
green olive this thing and so on so uh
Sy is under us proxy control now it's
not direct us proxy control uh there is
the involvement of Israel and Turkey as
well but that's the deal so what what
let's go back to the question what's the
question what's the U Us's primary
interest here okay so look Syria was
Russian and Iranian proxy Iran and
Russia were cooperating in Syria Russ
Russia has a couple of air has has a
naval base and an air base in Syria I
think they will have to evacuate these
I'm sure they'll be allowed to do it
quietly and without any fuss but yeah
Russia loses its leverage and its
presence in
Syria and Syria was the conduit through
which Iran could uh could connect with
Hezbollah in Lebanon because the
northern part of Iraq Etc I mean Iraq is
kind of to some extent Iran has a
presence in Iraq as well because of the
significant Shia population that you
have in Iraq so that's how through Iraq
via Syria Iran could connect with hisbah
in Lebanon now that is gone so Iran has
lost its leverage Iran has lost its
ability to project power here and so has
Russia so if you look at if you zoom out
you will see that all the nations except
Iran in this region the west Asia region
are now us proxies or US allies direct
or indirect stated or unstated except
for Iran so Iran has lost much if not
most of its power projection abilities
in the region they still have some uh
power projection ability in Iraq but
that's about it okay and Russia also
it's a big setback for them it's a
defeat it's a defeat but not a
catastrophic defeat for Russia so that
is the deal so obviously what the US is
trying to do is to uh expand their
sphere of influence
uh uh degrade Russia's capabilities in
the region and essentially they're
they're moving the geopolitical
chessboard so in such a way that Russia
is is retreating and they are going
forward that's what's happening and
obviously uh the long end game is to
defeat Russia and even Iran is a big big
piece on the geopolitical chessboard
which is why Iran could very much
face the
heat very
soon uh so it's not a Ukraine like
strategy it's a different strategy it's
not about when it comes to the Natural
Resources Etc I think
turkey has an eye on that and they will
certainly they've been enjoying the
natural resources which is the oil and
gas of the region of Syria for quite
some
time um so turkey uh will do that Israel
has its own agenda here but the for the
US it's all about containing Russia and
probably defeating
Iran so yeah that's the
deal Vikram geopolitical says Netanyahu
say
Israel will change the map of the Middle
East will Israel be successful in doing
this with the support of the
US okay let's go back to the map same
region Syria right Syria has fallen to
uh a rebranded Isis and Al-Qaeda kind of
thing yeah so-called Rebels who were
formerly called called terrorists by the
Americans now so nanahu has said that he
will Israel will change the map of the
Middle East so what's happened after
Assad fell is that uh Israel has started
expanding the buffer zone the so-called
buffer zone in the area and they have
been pounding various military locations
military Assets in Syria Syria had
probably the middle east's best
anti-aircraft
defenses all of th those have been taken
out in wave after wave of Israeli air
strikes they had an Air Force much of
which is now destroyed the helicopters
aircraft all have been destroyed so
Syria is no longer going to be a threat
to anybody in West Asia just like what
happened to Iraq in 2003 Iraq was
permanently removed as a threat to
anybody the same thing is now happening
to Syria and Israel is expanding see
there was this uh zone of contention
between Israel and Syria which was the
Golan Heights this region now Israel is
definitely in control of this area and
they are expanding uh the territory that
they
hold uh so yeah you could say that
Israel is physically expanding its
territory without making it official
they could be very close to Damascus by
now their tanks or whatever uh so they
will definitely not take Damascus
there's no point doing that so overtly
but they will take control of large
areas of the
region uh Jordan is a US Ally so Jordan
is fine and eventually this this
statement that naanyu has made that
we'll change the map of the Middle East
it could probably be aimed at Iran
because the the main
uh adversary from Israel's perspective
in the region what's left it's only Iran
so I you know I am not a fan of war war
is terrible but it's possible that Iran
could be at war with Israel or Israel
plus Us by this coming summer of 2025
it's
possible yeah that's where we are
now Vikram Ador says what kind of
geopolitical game is erdogan playing on
the one hand he appears friendly with
Russia he admires Putin and then he
causes the ouer of Assad which was
Russia's Ally at the same time Turkish
Fighters attacked us-based
SDF considering turkey is a NATO Ally of
the US what's happening it looks like
turkey is playing a double game against
Russia and the US the two superpowers
what's your take on this okay look yeah
uh erdogan is pretty friendly with uh
Putin he admires
Putin Etc that's a personal onetoone
relationship it has
no effect on geopolitical relations
international relations it's very
possible I mean I'm sure it's happened
lots of times that the leaders of two
adversarial Nations have a good equation
they're good friends they admire each
other and yet they're going to fight to
the
end because the national interest is
Paramount for a leader not your personal
interest or person personal friendship
with somebody so erdogan is friendly
with with Putin so what makes no real
difference he has his own Ambitions for
turkey he probably sees him as the
Sultan of a resurgent Neo Ottoman Empire
and he's trying to expand turkey's
geopolitical footprint and power
projection ability and territory in the
region and of course turkey we know is
uh a member of NATO an ally of the US
the Americans even have
allegedly uh nuclear weapons deployed in
Turkey which are in American hands not
Turkish hands that's the kind of closed
relationship uh turkey has with the US
and apparently they have attacked the
SDF which is a terrorist outfit a
rebranded Al-Qaeda or Isis which is are
fighting on behalf of the US in in Syria
and they've taken over Syria right Al
julani is their boss SDF yeah so uh
turkey always plays this game look I'll
tell you what makes turkey valuable from
a NATO perspective what makes turkey
valuable let's go to Turkey is this
region turkey's incredible Geo
geographical region it controls the in
the extremely valuable choke points
between the Black Sea and uh the ageny
which goes on into the Mediterranean
which means that if you go to
Istanbul uh you have the straight of
Bosphorus which connects uh the Black
Sea to the Sea of marmara and then you
have the Straits of
chakal or the dardel straight two
extremely vital geographical
geopolitical to points and turkey is the
owner the geographical owner of these
two choke points and that's why turkey
is so valuable and turkey has been rent
seeking enjoying rent seeking this
geographical location so turkey is very
valuable to the US to Nato uh and Russia
also has to ensure that turkey remains
on on on reasonable good terms with them
so turkey can play all kinds of
geopolitical games so they have been U
controlling certain parts of Northern
Syria for the past decade plus that's
one of the things they're doing and they
would like to take more B out of Syria
now now that Assad has fallen turkey uh
in the
1970s I think they took over the
northern part of Cyprus uh they invaded
Cyprus and they did that they Turks also
have a presence in Libya and North
Africa a military presence in this
region as as peace peacekeepers
peacekeepers allegedly and turkey would
also like to create a pan Turan Corridor
between turkey and all the Turkish
nations of of Central Asia uh and the
one nation that's in the way is Armenia
and that's why you had Wars between
turkey's proxy aeran and Armenia so
turkey is playing a whole game
geopolitical game of its own it has its
own Ambitions erdogan has its own
Ambitions and he uh will obviously play
the good old game of playing one giant
against another to gain Advantage for
himself and his Nation it's it's a
wellknown
very old set of tricks in the
geopolitical
Playbook okay let's take some questions
from the live
chat
um okay let's take this one Sumit J says
did the US blunder by starting the
Ukraine war reigniting Russian
patriotism and giving them a 1945 like
moment as they also Thrive
geopolitically and are independent of US
influence look technically you one could
argue that Russia started the Ukraine
war right because Putin is the one who
spe who who ordered the special military
operation which is now called the
Ukraine war but we know that he had no
choice he was forced to do this
otherwise Russia's national interest
would have been very deeply
compromised so yeah we know the US
forced him to do this he had they left
him with no choice uh is this a
blunder I think you know
geopolitically you know what's the aim
what's the objective in geopolitics
geopolitics is like a sport but in it's
a sport with no rules you make up your
own rules and the more more powerful you
are the more rules you can make or break
and the objective is to win win what the
objective is to win control contr
complete control and domination of the
entire planet that's the objective so
from the US perspective it's a
superpower it's a nation that is almost
Global power projection capabilities
they can intervene militarily almost
anywhere on the planet at 60 Minutes no
30 minutes notice whatever except for
Russia and
China uh and they would obviously like
to expand their sphere of influence they
would like to control
everything so uh the objective has
always been via NATO to keep expanding
eastwards eastwards until Russia's red
lines are breached and let then let's
see what Russia does uh so they've left
Russia with no no option and this kind
of
has transformed Russia in certain ways
the economy has changed there have
the sanctions that the Americans have
placed against them the Russian economy
has proven to be resilient thus far
they've been doing okay um the I'm sure
there's a lot of Social cohesiveness and
patriotism in Russia uh they are an
notari they have all the natural
resources you could ever ask for so the
industrial base is is getting better U
Russia always get gets better at War as
as a war gets longer so they are getting
better at
that was is was this a mistake it's a
mistake if Russia is able to defeat the
US uh and get more than what you expect
they would get so if Russia wins the
Ukraine war the US has
to uh make a compromise and Russia at
the partition the Ukraine or or takes
over Kio whatever then it's a defeat for
the US maybe you the maybe Ukraine is a
disposable assets are not much of a
defeat but if if Russia is able to
expand its sphere of influence as a con
consquence of the beginning of this war
then it's a it's a blunder by the US so
time will tell if it's a blunder or or
not right now things are kind of in a
state of quaa equilibrium the way it is
right now Ukraine it's a it's a long War
scenario that we are facing in Ukraine
stalemate kind of thing but it's a
statement the Russians can change like
that if they want to but uh they also
are being very cautious uh so I I can't
say right now if it was a blunder if
it's a it's a blunder if Russia is able
to turn the TBL of the US long term as a
consequence of the of this war being
ignited so time will tell us if this was
a
blunder right next
question a couple of questions about
Trump anant Pai and vickram
geopolitical why do you think Trump is
going after Justin Trudeau calling him
the governor of Canada and openly
pointing out the that Canada is a US
possession Trump addressed Trudeau as
Governor Justin and offered to make
Canada the 51st state of the US are the
relations between the two Nations going
to or the two leaders going to worson
under Trump's rule that's an interesting
question so what exactly has Trump done
Trump uh
Trump uh let's let's put that on the
screen shall we Trump's tweet or the
post that he put put out there let's put
that on the screen what did Trump say
here we have
it so uh Trump said this it was a
pleasure to have dinner the other night
with Governor Justin Trudeau of the
great state of Canada I look forward to
seeing the governor again soon so that
we may continue in our continue our
in-depth talks on tariffs and trade the
results of which will be truly
spectacular for all djt Donald J Trump
so that's what djt said J in trudo the
prime minister of Canada Trump called
him the governor
of the great state of Canada not the
independent Sovereign Nation of Canada
the state of Canada which means he's
implying that Canada is a state of the
US it's not an independent Sovereign
Nation it is a US possession and Trudeau
is merely a governor of the state he's
not a sovereign he's not a prime
minister of a Sovereign Nation so Trump
is essentially pointing out what I mean
if you know what's going on in the world
you should know that Canada is not a
Sovereign Nation Canada is is a nation
that
exists as a de facto Sovereign Nation
because the US allows it to exist that
way but Canada doesn't have an
independent foreign policy independent
uh Economic Policy everything Canada
does is merely as an extension of US
policy and no Canadian leader can dare
to go against any dictat of the US
impossible there's going to be very
serious consequences and that person
will be in trouble
so uh this is something that you don't
point out openly I mean there's there's
certain Norms that you follow uh you
don't say that the emperor has no
clothes right you don't say that but
Trump has gone ahead and say said it so
I'm glad he has made things very clear
Canada is a wasal it's a possession of
the US it's not an independent
nation uh what does it mean uh is Trump
going after
Trudeau maybe Trump doesn't like Trudeau
and I don't blame him I don't think
anybody likes Trudeau fenping doesn't
like Trudeau uh Trudeau uh Mr Putin
doesn't like Trudeau Mr Modi doesn't
like trudo I don't think any Madame Mone
doesn't like trudo at all you can't
stand the guy and I don't think Mr Trump
likes too either no one likes him the
guy how yeah so so maybe it's it's about
personal dislike that's why Trump may
have said this uh
does it mean the relations between the
two Nations will worsen no relations
will remain the
same the Canadian side may say a few
words here and there but their actions
will be completely
100% 3,000% aligned with us policy it
will make no difference whatsoever Trump
can taunt them all he wants the
Canadians can't do a thing about this so
I'm glad Mr Trump cleared this up and
made it very clear
that Canada is not a not an independent
Sovereign Nation it's merely a US
possession okay this question okay
Surendra Gupta and uh JMA Chand chandi
okay what's your view on the Atul subash
case who is responsible the judge the
wife his wife or the toxic feminist
ideology that's being spread through
Cinema I'm the mother of a 27-year-old
son who's working as a probationary
officer in SBI the recent case of Atul
subash who took his life due to his wife
in-laws and the corrupt Judiciary has
shaken the nation I'm really scared to
marry my son to any woman like that yeah
it's it's it's a horrific
case uh this young reasonably young man
an AI uh engineer machine learning uh
specialist from
Bangalore uh he put out a video on
Rumble more than 1 hour long in which we
when which he detailed everything that
he has gone through he put out all the
evidence that he has very substantial
evidence of what's happened to him and
then he took his life and this is not
some isolated case it happens very
frequently in India on a daily basis in
various parts of
India and he was obviously facing
harassment from his wife his in-laws
they were demanding all kinds of money
and he alleges that that that the judge
was taking the side of his wife and he
alleges that the judge was asking for
bribes several lak rupees and he alleges
that uh he's already paid I don't know
how many crores to the wife allegedly
and they keep on asking for more and
that sort of thing so he's left with no
and they've taken his son away from him
and so on uh so he has said that his
wife his in his
in-laws and the Judiciary and the judge
that's what he has said are responsible
for his suicide they have actually
induced him to commit suicide they've
encouraged him to commit suicide on
multiple occasions as that's what he
alleged so he's put all the evidence out
in public very meticulously was a very
meticulous person and he taken his life
extremely sad extremely tragic situation
and this is something that happens very
routinely in India he's not the only
person who who's gone through this uh
and it's it happens to men men not women
I mean I'm not saying women don't face
harassment or any problems but this is
something that happens to men more than
women so what's going
on uh so who's responsible for what
happened to him I think it's the
system that is
responsible the laws are heavily biased
towards
women why are the laws heavily biased
towards women and if a woman makes an
allegation uh
everything Rains Down on the man
everything can everything that can go
wrong can go will go wrong to him if a
man makes an allegation against a woman
no one takes him seriously and no one
nothing nothing is done so they will
take the woman's word if she makes an
allegation but never the man's word and
men must suffer apparently that's that's
how the entire system is is constructed
the legal system the laws are biased
against
men um so why did this happen first of
all it's because there is this narrative
that's been going around in our
education system in our
media uh Etc that in India women are
oppressed it's the feminist narrative
and women are are oppressed by men
because India is a misogynistic
patriarchal country Society we are a
society with serious defects we are a
backward primitive barbaric misogynistic
patriarchal evil
society and not Society but our culture
is like that Hinduism and that's why we
must make laws that are very strongly
Pro women and very strongly
anti-men and when and then the Judiciary
typically will take the side of the
woman but not the man
and that's why uh these laws exist and
there are all kinds of loopholes
apparently in the judicial process and
it's always the men who's the victim and
I'm not saying that women are never
victims I'm sure that are lots of cases
in a country of 1.4 billion in which
women have been oppressed and maybe
because of a few such cases such laws
were made but these laws can be very
easily
weaponized by unscrupulous people and uh
so that's what's happening so who's
responsible for this I think in India
when something goes wrong the
responsibility is spread out across the
system not one person in this case he
has been able to name the judge
allegedly right so he is alleged the the
judge is corrupt
and so on but overall the system the
laws who passed the laws the parliament
right it's not one person the whole
parliament pass the law and it's not one
law it's multiple
laws so there is that and then there is
the entire legal system that interprets
the laws in various different ways and
so on so you you can't pin down
responsibility on one person the entire
system is biased and allegedly corrupt
and of course like you mentioned this
toxic feminist ideology that's been
spread through Cinema that's been spread
through the education system you
know you have to have laws that are
equal for men and
women
equal but why are men and women not
equal under the in the eyes of the law I
mean isn't that the whole point maybe
it's not the point maybe the point of
feminism Etc is to make is to create a
divide between men and women to rip
Society apart to tear Society apart and
to atomize society and in in in our
civilization in our culture the family
is the unit of society but in feminist
ideology in the western worldview the
human the individual is the unit of
society and to make it happen that way
you to destroy the family the
institution of the family you tear it
apart look at the West marriages
invariably end in divorce most kids are
raised by single mothers not single
fathers single mothers typically and
Society is totally bankrupt over there
so they want to create the same system
here so it's the education system it's
it's this Cinema the media the
entertainment industry it's the
parliament it's the people you elect to
Parliament it is the political parties
you elect I'm not naming anyone maybe
they're all part of this Nar Shakti okay
but what about all
shaki um and so much more and the
Judiciary they interpret laws in in
their own way I'm not sure how right or
wrong it is I'm who am I to judge uh but
yeah so it's it's a terrible situation
and and men are facing the brunt of this
increasingly so what's my view I think
it's terrible we need to reform
everything we need to have laws that are
equal for everybody irrespective of your
gender I'm sure it can be done but
no they won't do it so yeah so many
problems in this country like this yeah
the second question I'm the mother of a
27y old son who's working is so and so
uh and I am really scared to marry my
son to any woman like that yeah
obviously you'll be scared obviously
you'll be scared I completely understand
so what's the solution to this obviously
your son has to marry right you you
can't you can't keep him unmarried
obviously he will want to marry maybe he
does hopefully he will want to
marry generally you want to marry right
you want to have a have a partner a
spouse so what do you do obviously
there's the danger that this sort of
thing may end up
uh happening to him that's the fear it's
a very real fear because it's a very
real danger so what do you do look you
to understand it it's it's it's not very
complicated actually if we look at it
from a certain perspective a marriage
between two individuals is an alliance
between two
families
okay and if something goes
wrong usually it's because there is a
lot of family involvement and one of the
parties the party that is doing the
oppressing of of of the spouse that is
doing the
oppressing of the of their of the
partner generally their family is
involved as is as it was in this case
the Atul subash case so
if so these days we have a lot of what
do we call love marriages I'm not saying
there's anything wrong with love
marriage okay love marriages are
perfectly good but if you are going to
have a love marriage you have to
understand what kind of background your
partner is coming from you to meet the
family you to understand the family
culture Etc very well and that has to
match to a certain extent with your own
culture and your old family's culture
the upbringing and all that if the two
families can't get along it's not going
to
work and it's not it could not work long
term and if you and generally if there
is something wrong you can see among the
family
members so you have to do your due due
diligence in arranged marriages it
always used to happen that way you know
there was always first family to family
contact and you would ask everybody you
know knew about the other family and you
would do a lot of due religions
understand everything and then you see
whether the two families are compatible
and then with the two individuals are
comp compatible but now apparently
arranged marriages are
bad so now uh that's so that's where we
are and then you have to go online to
shadi.com or whatnot. come to find a
partner because the old system is gone
and because so many people are
transplanted to places where they don't
their family doesn't exist like
metropolitan cities and all so they have
to find a spouse on their own so that's
all this thing my main thing the main
thing I would like to say is that to
ensure that something like this doesn't
happen to your
sons make sure that you understand the
other family very well and see that if
there are any red red flags over there
that's what I would say but yeah indan
India system is
ridiculously bad not just the education
system not just the entertainment
industry everything I mean so much needs
to be reformed the laws are terrible
many of these laws are terrible they are
so so strongly biased against one gender
they have to be G gender neutral laws
have to apply to everyone equally you
can't have special favors for one gender
at the expense of the other gender
that's terrible what are you encoding in
the laws it's going to destroy Society
in the long run that's what we are
seeing now terrible
situation okay let's take some questions
from the live
chat
uh Nick says be a responsible mother too
yeah yeah certainly
certainly uh I have already spoken about
UFO so we will not take that that's the
first question I took today I think
first or second
uh what other questions do we have
uh I'm not
sure RI says this is a light humorous
question are you a member of the deep
state of India they I don't see any deep
State existing in
India and if if there is one I certainly
am not I'm not part of
that
uh okay what else do we we have or
should I go back to the to the to the to
the okay Manan panchal says as an Indian
living in Europe what can we do to
improve the image of Indians amongst
foreigners I've lost I've noticed a lot
of discrimination lately on social media
against
Indians look if you are an Indian living
in a foreign country you have to
understand that you are an ambassador of
India in that country de facto you may
not be sitting in the embassy or the
consul or any of the consulates but as
an individual you are an ambassador of
your country and your culture and your
civilization in that country so you have
to be the best version of yourself there
are many Indians I've seen who go abroad
and they behave in very
borish manner borish fashion they will
litter like as if they're littering in
India or they will speak loudly and be
obnoxious and what not behave well if
you are living there you're not just a
tourist you're living there then always
have good manners and
and um make make the locals admire you
in whatever way either as a professional
if you are working in a company there
then work work harder work better than
the others if you're socializing always
be well well groomed neat healthy fit
all that always that sort of thing so
you have to always put your best foot
forward that's what you can do as an
individual to to improve the image of of
India among foreigners And if every
Indian does that then the image will
change very
rapidly uh the problem is that you know
lots of Indians behave poorly when they
travel abroad I'm talking about tourist
right now uh in know Nation like Bali
for example the Bal indes people always
saw us Indians as their cultural kin as
their cultural relatives but when travel
to Bali became cheap and lots of Indians
started visiting them they would try and
you know Indians behaved in a very cheap
manner try and uh try and get the best
deals for everything if something cost
let's say 100 Indonesian rupia they'll
say why not why don't you give it to me
for 20 Indian Indonesian rupia and try
and bargain and haggle and harass the
hell out of the
locals and uh so yeah so the image of
India took a beating has taken a beating
in balii Imagine in a place like Bali
the image of India has taking a beating
the the only Hindu part of Indonesia
where Hindus are in a majority so
Indians need to behave well in a
civilized manner in a respectful manner
when they travel abroad if you're living
abroad always put your best for put
forward and try to be far better than
the locals in every way possible that
way you can improve the image of India
let's go back to the
questions okay subba sub mundal says how
to win logically in a
situation for example for failure for
for rejections or for not achieving
expectations for something when the
brain is
occupied
emotionally yeah what do you do in a
situation where you have you experience
a setback in
life right what do you do when things
don't go
wrong how do you succeed from that from
that
position and especially when you are
feeling emotionally down when you when
something goes wrong you know
emotionally it's going to it's going to
affect you very badly so what do you do
about this right and how do you win from
there so you have
to okay it's easy to say be mentally
strong be this be that all that fine
control or emotions emotional people
usually Fair poorly ET it's easy to say
all that it's cliched but what's the way
of of getting out of a Sol of a
situation
logically so if you have tools logical
tools that will enable you to find the
right solution then you will first
resort to that instead of sitting down
and crying and being emotional right the
problem is most people don't have those
tools those logical tools problem
solving tools
so let me give you an example yeah so
let's say you are let's say it's the
1930s you are an Indian Freedom Fighter
revolutionary Freedom Fighter genuine
Freedom Fighter no not that fake ainsa
nonsense you're an Indian reevolu
tionary and it's occupied India right
British occupied India 1930s so you and
your friends you and your comrades you
break into a British occupation police
station to steal guns and ammunition now
you your comrades they take the guns
they break into the place they take the
guns ammunition Etc but you and another
comrade are caught by the British and
they take you to jail and they separate
you and this very wonderful nice British
jail Taylor he tells you and your
comrade the same thing he offers you
both a deal the same deal but separately
in separate
rooms so he says you were caught on
police station premises you are
trespassing this carries a one year
sentence but I know you and your friends
have stolen the guns but I can't prove
it I don't have the evidence I need your
testimony I need your confession so you
are facing a one-ear sentence but if you
confess I will set you free but your
partner will get a 10year sentence and
I'm offering your partner the same deal
if both of you confess your individual
testimony is no longer going to hold and
both of you will get a three-year
sentence so when you find yourself in
the situation you're going to be
terrified you're going to be fearful you
will be
dejected and you will me you'll probably
break down mentally that I'm facing a
10-year jail sentence that I'm facing
God knows what in in the jail
one year 3 years or 10 years right so
should you just break down emotionally
or should you resort to logic right so
you have to first tell yourself that if
if you are in jail for 10 years you
can't serve the nation so your priority
has to be to minimize your jail time and
you are not sure about your partner you
don't know whether he is reliable
whether he will stay quiet whether he
will confess whether he'll Break Down
Under Pressure mental pressure you don't
know what's what's going to happen so
the question is what strategy should you
choose what strategy should each
prisoner
choose okay so let's actually try and
calculate what strategy the prisoners
must must choose let's let's open an
Excel sheet and let me tell you how to
logically do this
thing okay how to logically find a
solution in a bad
situation so let's open an Excel
sheet here is a blank Excel sheet let's
let's zoomify in there okay so you have
you essentially have two prisoners right
you are a prisoner and your friend is a
prisoner so you are P1 let's say and you
have two
choices okay be
quiet or
confess and your comrade prisoner
too also has two choices be quiet or
confess so we're going to put it all
here okay prisoner to also has quiet and
confess now if you're quiet and you're
comrade is quiet you both get a one-ear
sentence so I'm getting putting one one
for both if you are quiet and prisoner
to confesses then you get a 10year
sentence and this guy gets nothing he's
out if you confess and the other guy
stays quiet you get zero years he gets
10 years and if both of you confess it's
three years each so what should you do
is the question right so to answer this
question you have to essentially you you
have to
consider each choice in isolation so
let's see things from p1's perspective
that is Prisoner one's perspective let's
assume that he
knows that P2 will will stay quiet okay
let's let's assume that he knows that P2
will stay quiet and so let's not
consider at all what happens to P2 you
are only concerned with with what
happens to you so instead of p2s one
we'll put a question mark here and over
here also we will put a question mark so
we know that P2 will stay
quiet so if P1 stays quiet he gets a
one-ear sentence if P1 confesses he gets
Freedom zero
years so clearly confession is a good
strategy for P1 if P2 remains quiet but
what if P2 confesses so let's let's look
at that scenario okay let's look at that
scenario we will take this and put it
here so now we know that P so now P1
knows that P2 will confess so P2 P1 if
he stays quiet he's going to get 10
years if he confesses he going to get
only three
years and we'll put question marks here
because we not concerned about what
happens to the other guy this is just
logic so once again confession is the
better option here also confession is
the better option so for prisoner one
irrespective of what prisoner 2 does
confession is the better option this is
simply logic now let's look at things
from From p2's perspective okay let's
let's look at things from p2's
perspective uh so once again let's copy
this and put it
here and let's say that uh P2 knows that
P1 will stay
quiet so in that case what
happens so in that case we'll put
question marks here and
here so From p2's perspective he knows
P1 will St quiet so if P2 stays quiet he
will have one year if P2 confesses he
will have zero years in in jail so
confession is the better option and once
again let's see what happens if P1
confesses so we'll once again put
question marks here and we'll once again
put a question
mark here so so if P1 if P1 confesses
then P if P2 stays quiet he gets 10
years if he confesses he gets three
years so it's clear that in both cases
even for P2 confession is the better
option and for P1 also confession is the
better option so if you look here
confession is 3 three both guys get
three years and if you stay quiet both
guys take one year get one year so why
is
confession the better option clearly
quiet quiet is better than confess
confess
however the problem is that from a
logical perspective a promise to remain
silent is not
sustainable so the quiet quiet option
both guys staying quiet that option that
that outcome is inherently unstable and
the option for both to confess is an
inferior solution but it is
sustainable so both prisoners you and
your comrade need to confess and that is
the right
solution there is no morality here there
is no emotion here it's just logic so
what I've just showed you is essentially
the first lesson you will be taught in
Game
Theory so if you
want to know how to win logically in a
situation where you have failed you have
to learn Game Theory it's all logic
there's no emotions there and if you and
you can learn game theory in two weeks
if you study two hours a day if it's not
that difficult all you need is basic
math you can learn game theory in two
weeks take a textbook learn it once you
have that tool in Your Arsenal you will
and and you find yourself in a bad
situation you will your first response
will not be to cry or to feel dejected
it will be to find a solution via Game
Theory so my point is if you went to if
you want to win logically in any
situation of failure learn Game Theory
learn logic learn how to apply these
these learnings in real life situations
that's how you win logically in any
situation all right it's all about logic
and causality learn Game Theory it's not
that
difficult okay let's take some more
questions from the comments what do we
have what do we have um I have no idea
how much money is sufficient to retire
in 2035 look okay this's this question
uh jig whatever the name is uh how much
money will be sufficient to retire in
2035 also once one also once one becomes
financially free in life what do you
what to do how to deal with the
meaninglessness of life it's a big
question okay two questions in one
look in today's money in India if you
want to have retirement kind
of bank balance you would need a few
crores so that you never have to work
work again in your in your life and your
dependents also never have to work again
in your life maybe 5 10
crores and then you live modestly within
your means and you can invest some of it
and you'll have an income for Life
essentially maybe 5 10 crores you may
need uh in 2035 we don't know what the
exchange rate of the Indian rupe versus
gold or versus the US doar will be so I
don't know about that 2035 in today's
money if you want to have a reasonably
secure life um maybe 5 10 Crow is enough
I know it's a huge amount of money most
people have never seen a crore but
that's the kind of situation we live in
today yeah that's that's the kind of
value money has today so if you
extrapolate that to 2035 so ask yourself
a very simple question let's say
hypothetically 10 crores is what you
want to have in your bank balance okay
bank
account ask yourself a very simple
question how much gold can you buy for
10 CR
rupes let's say it is X kilos or X grams
let's say so let's say you could buy X
Gams of gold for 10 CR
rupees then that same X Gams of gold
whatever it is worth in rupees in 2035
that's the money you need in 2035 so I
think you have to invest in things like
gold not all of it but a certain amount
at least of your money you to invest in
gold or or such assets that don't really
lose value over time gold is never going
to lose its value you know that and gold
is in appreciating in value so I think
that's uh the the kind of thing you have
you need to have um maybe 5 10 crores in
today's money how to deal with the
meaninglessness of life it's look why is
life
meaningless why does it have to be
meaningless you have to find your own
meaning in life historically our culture
our civilization it used to tell us what
the meaning of life is but today
everybody is a drift because we don't
know our culture we are completely
deracinated Ro it's not your fault
anyone's fault our education system is
ensured that we are completely
disconnected from our culture so and
that's why we don't know what's the
meaning of life and we are lost yeah we
are all victims we are all victims in
that matter so what to do you have to
find your own way your own meaning of
life either you can become religious or
or read about culture which tells you
exactly what life is or you have to find
your own definition of meaning in life
maybe for some people meaning in meaning
in life is to have a big goal and work
towards that and Achieve that goal
hopefully maybe I want to have have $100
million by the age of so and so that's a
big goal and that gives you meaning in
Life or I want to build something I want
to build a new company and have it have
this sort of Revenue or I want to start
a university let's say um in so many
years or whatever have some big
ambitious goal which is very hard to
achieve and then work very hard towards
that that can give you meaning in Life
or maybe I want to have these number of
kids and they should all be settled very
well and they should their life should
be happy maybe that's a go so you have
to find your own meaning in life if you
are completely disconnected from your
heritage your culture so uh if you don't
if you don't find meaning in life then
it's going to be very hard to live life
you know you you'll feel clueless you
you'll feel aimless you'll feel like
you're wandering of drift and that's not
a good situation to be in in life okay
so find meaning how do you find how do
you start by how do you begin the
process of finding meaning in life you
to first know who you
are most people
don't know who they are they spend their
whole
lives they go through their entire lives
without really knowing who they
themselves are how can you know who you
are you to spend time alone there are
lots of people I know who are scared of
being alone they are frightened of being
alone learn how to en learn how to enjoy
being with yourself then try to
understand yourself who am I what are my
likes what are my dislikes what are my
strengths what are my what are my
weaknesses what are my hopes what are my
aspirations what did I want to do when I
was a little kid what what did I love
what did I enjoy and that that maybe
gives you some kind of purpose and path
in life so it's a it's a process you
won't be able to solve get the answer in
in one hour one day one week it's a
process maybe it'll take you a year or
so maybe it'll take you three months but
you have to introspect and do that and
then you to decide what your what life
means for you okay
right uh okay next question Ric says why
do highly ambitious people with average
Talent achieve greatness in the long
term while extremely talented people
without ambition end up with just
average or above average success in life
Talent is of no use if you are
lazy if you are not capable of working
hard if you're not willing to work
harder than anybody else because as you
rise higher in
life as you achieve more you'll find
that
everybody is talented at that level
so what
differentiates you from the others how
much work you willing to put in how hard
you willing to
work uh you will see so many talented
people who don't succeed in life you
will see so many talented Sports people
I'm sure you can name a few just like
that who were super talented but failed
did not achieve what they were capable
of Pakistan let's said let's talk about
Pakistan cricket Muhammad Amir he he
burst onto the scene as a left arm fast
Bower
about 10 12 15 years ago incredibly
talented it looked like he will go Way
Beyond Wasim akam where is he today
incredibly talented person
but perhaps something wrong with his
attitude perhaps something wrong with
with his work ethic whatever and you
will see on the other hand people with
average to not great talent but who are
super hardworking and who will go ahead
of everyone so my point is Talent is
useless with without the willingness to
work incredibly hard okay and you can
only work incredibly hard if you're are
in incredibly
ambitious otherwise you you will not be
motivated to work super super hard so
you need ambition you need the work
ethic the willingness to work really
really hard to to work and to put on put
in more work than anybody else and then
if you also are talented then nobody can
beat you so
yeah okay PR Paul says space X's growth
in L in launch numbers is nothing short
of revolutionary going from Once launch
in 2006 to 100 in 2024 thus
far uh how do you see this Relentless
space shaping the future of space
exploration in the global space economy
does this level of dominance by a
private company indicate a shift in
power dynamics traditionally held by
governments and space programs and how
should India respond to this new era of
private sector driven space
advancements yeah Space X uh I've spoken
about this many times it is uh what it's
doing is revolutionary they have done
more launches this year than India has
ever done it in in its entire career
ISRO has ISRO did its first launch in
1979 and since 1979 until today ISRO has
done I think 97 or 98 launches of
rockets and SpaceX has done more
launches more rocket launches this year
than ISRO has has done
throughout so yeah that's where we are
so SpaceX has taken the World by storm
now does it mean that private
companies are going to be more powerful
than governments now absolutely not
absolutely not there is no change no
shift in power dynamics traditionally
governments own space programs but now
these private companies who have space
programs and that's why private
companies are more powerful than
governments no
see Elon Musk is the sole owner of
SpaceX as far as I can remember I think
he is right SpaceX is not publicly
traded so Elon Musk owns SpaceX at least
the majority of
SpaceX and he's a US
citizen now
if Spa if Space X were doing things that
are not useful to the US government the
US government can shut things
down if SpaceX decides that we will do
work that will benefit all Humanity not
just the government of the US not just
the citizens of the US but humans all
over the planet we will help equally
everybody you think the US government
will allow that
no SpaceX is able to succeed because the
US government wants it to succeed
because the US government directly or
indirectly owns
everything look at open
AI open AI right chat GP they're the
guys they're the ones who that's the
company that has created chat
gbd there's a
retired US Government guy general or
whatever who's on board the company why
do you think he's on board the company
because see what the US
does is they create they allow a couple
of players in a in a sector in AI
there'll be like two three players big
players no more than that will be
allowed only the state San the
government sanctioned companies
the the companies favored by the US
government will be allowed and they will
do exactly what the government tells
them and other companies if they're
trying to launch a new startup in AI
they should just forget about it because
the field is now full filled up
similarly with space launches SpaceX
does everything now NASA NASA I don't
know why it even
exists yeah they still have these
programs you know this scientific
programs and all that they continue with
that but
uh so SpaceX essentially whether you
realize it or not whether it is official
formal legal or not it's owned by the
US so these are simply extensions of the
US policy and uh SpaceX has starlink
thousands of satellites in Earth orbit
you think it's only for giving for for
providing Internet space internet I'm
sure these satellites all have
surveillance capabilities of various
kinds and these satellites probably give
the US the ability to conduct
24x7 surveillance of the entire
Globe I'm speculating I don't have any
evidence but satellites can be
multi-purpose
right uh and with the advances in
technology you don't need a lot of space
on a satellite or a lot of weight on the
satellite to have extra
functionality so Space
X is powerful yeah but it's an extension
of the US government so
I don't see these power dynamics
changing at
all this only makes the US government
more powerful it doesn't take power away
from them it augments their power that's
where we
are and you could say that Elon Musk
is kind
of a member a visible member of that
entity that everyone speaks about the
Deep state
okay sudip Kumar Roy says how did India
fool the CIA and the Deep State and go
nuclear you're talking about pokran 2 in
right let's go to the map and take a
look at pokran
too at pokran the
region uh the geographical region so
it's in Rajasthan isn't it uh where in
Rajasthan let's simply search for it
pokran pokran Rajasthan and we zoom into
it so it's a village and over here
nearby you have the location where
everything happened let's take a look at
the uh satellite
images uh what do we have
[Music]
here okay pokran nuclear test location
pokran one and this may be pokran 2
perhaps there's a helipad over here and
so on so this is where it happened okay
so India did the first did its first
nuclear test in
1974 it was called operation smiling
Buddha or something and after that the
Indian government put that
on on ice and said that we have
demonstrated our technological
capabilities and that's it we are a
peaceful Nation we don't want nuclear
weapons we just wanted to show that we
can do it and then we went to sleep and
then in 1998 when prime minister waj
came to power he immediately uh
instructed the scientists the engineers
at BARC Baba atomic Center and and Dr
and whoever else everybody to put
together
uh a number of nuclear devices that
would be tested as soon as
possible and that's how the test
happened now how did India fool the the
CIA and deeps and all so at the time the
Americans already had surveillance
satellites spy satellites that would and
and pokran was an area of special
interest because they knew that the
first test happened there and if you
want to do a nuclear test which is an
underground test you have to start
digging the place and dig shafts and do
a lot of activity to prepare for the
test and if you do that it's going to be
very easily visible on satellite
images and then you obviously have to
transport the nuclear weapons from BARC
Baba Atomic Research Center in Mumbai
all the way to Rajasthan and you have to
obviously ensure that these weapons
remain safe so you'll have a big armed
escort and all so that's also very
visible so that these are tell telltale
signs red flags that will immediately
set the alarm bells ringing in the in in
Washington or wherever and they will
know that they would have come to know
that India is planning to do a nuclear
test and then they can apply tremendous
pressure and prevent India from doing it
in in a variety of ways so the the key
was to ensure that they never got wind
of the fact that we are planning a test
so what India the government of India
did was that all the preparations pokran
were done in the night all the equipment
that was used to dig the shaft and all
that was used in the night and moved
back far away before day before Daybreak
all the sand and the and the soil that
came out of the shafts it was all
arranged meticulously to look like sand
dunes and in Rajasthan and pokran that
area you have sand dunes naturally
occurring sand dunes so it was all made
to look like that so that's how um and
and routine activities continued in the
the region uh so the Americans never got
to know that something is happening here
then the nuclear weapons the devices the
the devices themselves were moved from
BARC in Mumbai to the airport in Mumbai
under very light guard in unmarked
trucks just regular trucks and they were
flown to I think jelo Wherever by a
military aircraft it's a routine
military flight and then they were
transported to the pokran range Al under
almost no escort no
security and that's how the CIA was
fooled and when this happened everybody
was caught of guard including the
Americans until prime minister vaj I
think in the evening announced in a
press conference that India has
conducted three underground nuclear
tests and so on it's a very famous uh
video clip that is available on YouTube
so that's how India was able to fool the
in in the Deep State and uh test those
nuclear
weapons right next question how do we
how do we have different colors in the
universe what's the smallest thing that
it say own color do different types of
atoms have their own colors and we
derive colors from there what are colors
what is
color color is see what we perceive as
color what our eyes what our mind
perceives as color is simply
electromagnetic waves of different
wavelength and frequencies frequency
wavelength two sides of the same coin
so electromagnetic waves have very
characteristic wavelengths and
frequencies and these
frequencies are interpreted by our eyes
and our mind as
colors but the real world there's no
color it's just electromagnet magnetic
waves but to make the world appear
similar to us we color code it in as
actual color so you have so you have red
and you have blue blue and you have
brown and yellow and white and whatnot
all all that so we have we don't have
actually we don't have colors we have
electromagnetic waves of different
wavelengths and frequencies some of
these are in the infrared range which we
can't see some of them are in the
ultraviolet range that we can't see some
of these are extremely high frequency
waves called gamma rays and so on so so
that's why we have different colors we
perceive colors in the universe because
the universe is filled with
photons of different wavelengths what's
the smallest thing that has its own
color I don't think electrons have their
have a color I don't think protons so
electrons
protons uh neutrons don't have
color but atoms have color why do atoms
have color it's because atoms can emit
electromagnetic radiation atoms can emit
photons so that's why atoms
if they emit a photon they emit light of
a certain color so you know the hydrogen
Spectrum it's very Lyon Bal or pasture
bracket fund series and all that if you
study Physics at the college level you
will memorize that stuff so you have all
these if you if you look at the hydrogen
atom and you analyze it in a
spectrometer you have all these series
of you know bands of light and all that
and the sodium spectrum is very famous
the sodium double doublet yellow the the
dist characteristic color yellow so
these are all the consequence of of
photons being emitted by these various
elements hydrogen sodium Etc if you look
at the sodium metal it it looks brownish
in if you look at Copper for example
copper not sodium sodium looks whitish
if you look at copper copper is an
element made up of copper atoms it looks
brownish in in
color uh
sodium but uh copper sulfate looks blue
color so it depends on the kind of light
the frequency of the light that is
emitted when the atoms or molecules are
excited so that's why different types of
atoms have have different kinds of
elements actually not atoms but elements
have different colors that's why it is
so yeah okay let's take some more
questions from the
comments from the from the live
chat McLovin says is there a book to
learn game theory for non-math people
look the math that is involved in game
theory is very very basic math you don't
need calculus you don't need
differential equations you don't need uh
linear algebra or anything you just need
basic you don't even need
trigonometry uh to do Game Theory just
basic math is algebra needed maybe to a
certain extent
basic basic algebra maybe needed perhaps
if I recall but uh yeah so so don't be
worried about the math the math in game
theor is pretty simple if you have a
high school education probably you you
have it covered is there a book look I
don't remember any book five for Game
Theory uh you go to Amazon and you
search for Game Theory textbooks pick
the one with the highest
ratings and and should not be a book
with three three ratings all five star
should be a book with let's say 100 or
or 50 plus ratings which is above four
stars then it tells you that that book
is reasonably good um I don't remember
right now it's been a long time since I
studied Game Theory but yeah it's
something you can learn fast uh you can
go on Amazon or whichever whichever
website you buy from and just search for
Game Theory textbooks and pick the one
which is which has lots of ratings and
high ratings and it should and
preferably keep it small there are books
textbooks with like 300 Pages 400 pages
long don't go for those go for a slim
textbook that just go cuts to the Chase
and gives you gives you the
basics uh yeah so so I don't remember
any but that's how you would find a good
textbook for Game
Theory and that's the same question that
Shanks is
asking uh a book to learn Game Theory
let let's let's go to Amazon and if I
can do
that uh so I'm opening the Indian
website the Indian Amazon okay and let's
go to books and now let's search for
Game
Theory Game Theory so what do we have we
have this book which has 36 ratings and
it's 3.9 I would prefer games that have
four plus star ratings this is a very
venerable book by John vyan and Oscar
Morganstern morganstein Stern it's a
very old book old book it has 4.4 stars
out of five and 103 reviews which is
good this one seems good game theory by
Steven T is 162 reviews 4.5 how many
what's the page length how many pages
416 it's too much for me I would ra um
416 is Too
Much Game Theory a very simple
introduction and so on so I think you
should look at this and and see what's
the page how many pages these books have
uh so for example this book has four out
of five which is decent and and it has a
100 pages so maybe it's good but does it
have the math or is it
simply yeah so so essentially that's how
you would do it that's how you would do
your research about Game Theory
textbooks I don't remember any right now
so I can't tell you the names it's been
too long but yeah that's how you would
go about doing it find books with very
good reviews and high
ratings
okay let's see game theory 101 is a good
book okay good all
right
um SN says I'm 19 years old I'm in
college I struggle with loneliness I
have no connections of friends and I
have failing grades I have bad habits
like smoking what do you suggest I
do okay yeah uh you have to turn your
life around and uh pretty
rapidly so you have to ask yourself why
are
you why why you have failing grades why
are you addicted to something like
smoking why are you
lonely are do you have failing grades
because you are unhappy or you're facing
some problems in life in family at home
or because of some financial problems so
I don't know what exactly it is that is
causing these symptoms loneliness no
connection with friends bad grades and
bad habits these are symptoms of
something
deeper maybe it's
you're not happy at home perhaps I'm
guessing Okay I don't know you but what
could possibly cause something like
this
maybe your financial situation isn't
great or maybe your parents you don't
get along well with with your parents or
maybe something else not sure what it is
so whatever is the root cause of these
issues you to you to identify that and
you have to address that you to solve
that and once the root cause goes away
it will be easier to change the things
like see why does somebody typically
have failing grates maybe they don't
study I mean you will have failing rates
only if you don't study or if you don't
study properly if you have the time
needed to study but you are
distracted then you will have failing
grades but if you don't have the time
because of other problems then also you
will have failing grades and similarly
the other things so you have to find the
root cause of these symptoms and address
that root cause and then once that is
addressed rest then you have to take
each of these symptoms
individually and address that so how do
you quit smoking there's
no I think it's only through willpower
that you can quit smoking you can take
those uh chewing gums right nicotine
chewing gums and all or patches or
whatever that can help you beat the the
the
addiction U so that's how you do
supposedly quit smoking failing grads
you to concentrate you to find time to
to study and study regularly you to be
disciplined if you have no connections
on friends then you have to kind of
change your personality and try to be
more outgoing and try to find try to
find something in common with other
people Etc so you know it's it's uh it's
not possible for me to give you a
solution right away without knowing you
in person but first of all you to
address you to identify the root cause
of all these problems generally there
are lots of disparate problems that are
seemingly disconnected but they are all
tied to one single big problem you have
in life you first find that address it
solve it and then once it is solved it
will be easier easier for you to address
all these other
issues I wish you the best my friend I
wish you the best do well in
life okay
um okay let me go back to some of the
questions I've taken from the live chat
[Music]
um okay Sunil says a couple of weeks ago
a mai leader politician MP performed the
Haka dance in the New Zealand parliament
are the Maori people different from the
Australian
Aborigines that's a good question so
let's go to the map let me uh put the
map on the screen and let's find out the
region that we're talking about so
where's the
map here's the map the mai people are
native to New Zealand
okay uh and the Haka dance is a
traditional War dance that they perform
uh if you have ever watched rugby then
the New Zealand team it's called the All
Blacks in rugby they are known to
perform the Haka dance uh before a match
starts in front of their adversaries
their opponents and it's kind of the the
the objective is to intimidate the
adversary so the mai have historically
been a warlike people and they according
to to the evidence that we have it looks
like they first arrived in New Zealand
around some somewhere around the 1200s
or 1300s somewhere around that time and
where did they come from they came from
further eastwards they the the maoris
are Polynesian people the origin of the
Polynesian people seems to be in
Taiwan about 5,000 6,000 years ago and
from there the poian people apparently
spread all across the the Pacific region
uh in Hawaii you have the Hawaiian
people who are a poian people uh if you
go to rapan
hungara which is I believe Easter yeah
eastern island you you had Polynesian
people there they're not there anymore
if you look at French Polynesia Samoa
Etc Tonga all are inhabited new calonia
all are inhabited by Polynesian peoples
so the mai people are a Polynesian
people they first arrived about 800 or
so years ago
in New Zealand and they are not related
to the Australian Aboriginal people the
true natives the true uh indigenous
people of Australia are the so-called
Australian
Aborigines and they first appeared or
arrived in Australia about 50 or 60,000
years before today so the mai arrive in
New Zealand roughly 800 years ago when
the Australian natives first arrived in
Australia about 50 or 60,000 years
before
today huge huge
difference okay so the Maori are very
different from the Australian Aboriginal
people crazy dude says do you think
India should have land
redistribution due to centuries of
colonization the zamindar system imposed
by the by the by the Turks Etc land
ownership especially in regions like
Punjab Etc has been given predominantly
to the elites the handpicked Elites of
the foreign colonizers who
disproportionately own majority of land
living the common people with little
remaining very good
question today in India most people
don't have land most people struggle to
buy a one bedroom flat in a metropolitan
City lots of people in this country
maybe the majority of people don't
actually own land many people live on
rented and all that why is that a
thousand years ago everybody had land
everybody had ancestor land that was
passed on from their ancestors and
everybody had land so what happened then
you had the Turks who came in who
colonized India and they took away the
they stole the land from the natives and
gave it to zamindars that handpicked
Elite who would then tax the
natives and and collect the money and
pass it on to the to the sultan
and that's what happened and then you
have the the Europeans who came in the
British came in the British imposed the
riot F system the riot act the riat Vari
system which essentially rendered every
person in India landless they took away
the land and then they allowed people to
do subsistence farming on small Parcels
of land and there to give a backbreaking
amount of Revenue to the British so
that's what happened in the past
thousand or so years 700 or so years so
that rendered us landless and then after
1947 after the transfer of power from
the the colonizers to the to the
handpicked Indian Elites in
1947 uh the government of India came in
possession of a lot of land and the
people who who owned land in 1947 were
essentially the the handpicked Elite of
the
British uh so some Indians became
extremely wey as a consequence of colon
ation but the rest of India the majority
of Indians became incredibly poor India
had a life expectancy of 31 in 1947
India had a per capita GDP which was
abysmal India's cumulative GDP was less
than 2% of the world's GDP down from 33
34% in in the 1700s so that's what the
British did so everybody became landless
most Indians became landless so what
should have happened in
1947 was land redistribution
land should have been every Indian I
mean what is freedom freedom what is
Independence Independence means
everybody has some land
again all the wrongs that were done by
the colonizer should have been undone in
1947 or in a period of time 1947 onwards
all the British laws should have been
removed and Indian law should have been
brought in the British institutions
should have been dissolved and Indian
institutions based in Indian culture and
civilization should have been brought
should have been created over a period
of time maybe 5 10 years and there
should have been land redistribution in
1947 that never
happened so a lot of land was given by
the British to the church in
India and the church and the church was
typically given land on 99 year
leases and those leases have
expired but the church still has has
those lands and they have those
buildings on top of those lands in India
today
uh the church the Catholic church is
India's largest or second largest
landowner non-government
landowner so the government probably is
the largest landowner I think maybe the
wak board is the largest landowner I'm
not sure but the Catholic church is
after comes next so they don't really
own the land the land was given on Lees
it was Indian Land given to a foreign
entity so that should have been undone
those Lees should have been declared
null and void in
1947 that never happened and today those
Lees have expired but the government of
India dares not take the land back for
for for its people so even today we are
too
scared to undo the evils of
colonization we're too
scared even today's government is
scared and when it comes to land
redistribution you can't do it today it
should have been done in
1947 today it will be seen as a travesty
by a lot of
people so we had the opportunity to to
start the process of decolonization in
1947 it has never started it has not
even started
today so today you can't do re to do
land redistribution because too much
water has passed under under the bridge
since 1947 too much has happened too
much of land has been bought legally by
people will you take over the land they
bought legally after after 47 you can't
do that lots of companies lots of
Industries have bought land legally lots
of people have bought land legally small
Parcels of land big parts of of land or
whatever how can you take that away now
and redistribute it it should have been
done in 1947 you can't do it today big
opportunity
lost what is
independence if you are if you were
landless and dirt poor in during British
during the British occupation of India
and the same situation persists after 47
then what is the meaning of Independence
for the common person there was no
Independence everything stayed the same
just you just had new
overlords so was it really
Independence that's the question
okay rishab munti says this year a
virologist named Bata halasi cured her
third stage breast cancer by developing
her own vaccine if it's true then it can
be a breakthrough in medical Sciences it
can be a blessing for many cancer
patients uh then why do scient
why have scientists all over the world
not why are they not doing research on
it and why relevant stakeholders are not
initiating any action to Implement such
treatment as uh soon as
possible um so this lady is a biochemist
she's an infectious dis disease
researcher so she was around 50 or
something and she already had a couple
of breast cancer diag diagnosis before
this
event so I think she had undergone a
mastectomy which is the removal of the
breast tissue Etc but then the cancer
reoccurred in the same time place so
what she did was that she uh she studied
the literature the scientific literature
that's available and she decided to uh
use an unproven treatment I'm not sure
what the treatment is called but it
involves viruses so she chose to Target
the tumor with two different viruses I
think consecutively probably not
simultaneously and she did that over a
period of I don't know two or three
months so she prepared this stre
treatment with research grade material
that she herself made and one of her
colleagues administered the treatment to
her it was injected directly into the
tumor and that cured the
lady and then she obviously felt as a
scientist she felt the responsibility to
publish these findings and when she did
that she wrote she wrote down the paper
which was co-authored with other
colleagues and whenever she
submitted for submitted this paper for
publication to a journal she got a
rejection it was rejected more than a
dozen times by more than a dozen
journals and eventually it was published
and apparently it's they kept rejecting
it because this research involved
self-experimentation and apparently
self- experimentation is bad the lady
was about to
die so why would she not
self-experiment right it was almost like
a death death sentence the second or
third re recurrence of the same
cancer uh and there's been a lot of uh
negative articles written about her for
example in the journal Nature that this
is a very bad precedent and other
researchers should not do that and all
that I don't see anything wrong with
what she did uh
so I'm glad she was able to say herself
through her own expertise and our own
research
uh excuse me and the U methods she use
will definitely be a blessing for many
cancer patients I'm not sure if nobody
is taking it forward there's been a lot
of backlash against what she did
self-experimentation but she proved that
this technique
works and I'm sure that people will take
it forward so the the criticism and the
backlash has been to
against her towards her because she did
something that's frowned upon in
Academia in the academic world
self-experimentation you have to do a
double bind
bind you
know trials and all that there's a
certain way to do it you don't do it on
yourself and that's why she's been
criticized but she got the results and
she proved that it works so I don't see
anything wrong with that the the
academic system worldwide has become
very uh aifi
very regressive there's a lot of group
think there's a lot of resistance to
Innovation and to uh differing ideas and
differing methodologies and techniques
and things like that it's very
problematic so I'm I'm glad she did that
and now I'm sure people will take it
forward and use
that the the the treatment that she
discovered or used in scientific uh in
in Medical Treatments going forward I'm
sure
okay let's take some more questions from
the live chat
now Spartan bhagwa says shouldn't every
dharmic male or female learn how to
fight I recently started learning MMA it
has helped me realize the importance of
mental toughness and power of the mind I
think everybody should learn how to
fight uh irrespective of your gender
male female doesn't matter everybody
should be fit should be strong everybody
should lift weights if you are a female
it doesn't mean you should not lift
weights it doesn't mean you should not
get strong and lifting weights will not
make a female fat or large or masculine
it doesn't happen unless you
take hormones or steroids otherwise it's
fine and every male also should lift
weights and learn how to how to handle
themselves because it's possible someday
you may be attacked by somebody who
knows whatever uh so yes everybody
should learn self-defense everybody
should develop their body and make it
strong physically strong you need to be
like stronger than average yes and if
you can learn MMA or whatever craft Maga
or whatever it's good please do that so
yeah you can't have a strong mind
without having a strong body you can but
having a strong body will automatically
make you feel mentally strong so you got
to do that so I would encourage
everybody to ensure that you are
physically fit and strong
wrong and yeah and you'll know how to
defend
yourself Anamika says could it be that
with Trump in power now Narendra Modi
will face less difficulty in the 2029
elections I think 2029 is too far away
way too far away you know what they say
a week is a long time in politics we're
talking about four and a half years
right now uh with Trump in power things
will change the equation between the US
and India will change somewhat not not a
lot the US the US will still keep
pressurizing India they will still
leverage Bangladesh East Pakistan West
Pakistan against India they will
continue playing whatever games they
playing they will still keep on going
after adani or whoever is um
whichever industrialist is is aligning
himself geopolitically with the Indian
national interest they will go after
those people um they will try and
curtail India's growth they will do all
that but it may be less harsh and less
vituperative than the Biden
Administration
um so yeah things will change somewhat
but I think 2029 is way too far away
what will be Mr Mod's age in 29 what's
his age right now I wonder let me let me
quickly uh let's let's Google Mr modi's
age nendra Modi age how old is he he's
74 in 2024 in 29 is going to be what
it's going to be
79 we have to ask ourselves do we want a
79y old prime minister the question is
will Mr Modi himself want to run for
election as prime minister again in 79
at the age of 79 are you in the right
physical mental
shape or space to take on the
responsibility of being a prime minister
I'm not sure
uh look I I don't want to speculate as
to who's going to be the prime ministri
candidate of the BJP in 29 but maybe it
could be possibly somebody else apart
from Mr Modi so we don't
know my main point is 2029 is way too
far
away with Trump coming coming in office
in January next year in about a month's
time slightly More Than A month's time
things will change for India and the US
the relationship probably the
relationship will improve to a certain
extent
and then we can use that better
relationship to to to have a better
partnership and uh we'll take it from
there
okay okay
[Music]
um geopolitical du says do you think
China will take threats seriously from
from Ur Muslims to liberate East
turkistan China takes its National
Security extremely seriously and China
doesn't tolerate
terrorism or
separatism so yes there have been
threats from Syria from Ur Muslims who
have been fighting in the so-called
Rebel forces there have been threats
they will now return to sang East
turkistan or whatever and fight against
the Chinese government to liberate that
and obviously if they are fighting on
behalf of the rebels this the rebranded
al-Qaeda rebranded Isis obviously they
are us assets
these Ur Muslims who fighting there so
if they go and fight against China then
it's going to benefit the
US so China will take that very
seriously China takes these things very
seriously yes they do and they will will
crack down very hard on any such
activity pun says Indian submarine
program delayed again okay I'm not aware
of what has happened which may made you
say this I'm not aware maybe it's true
uh which submarine program are you
referring to the nuclear submarine
program the standard regular submarines
the p75 I project which one uh but I
don't know which one but yeah these
projects they move along very slowly
India needs lots of
submarines India should have a minimum
of minimum bare minimum 50 we don't even
have 20 right now and we are procuring
submarines at snails plays a glacial
pace so yeah this is and submarines are
the most important Naval asset in the
20th century not aircraft carrier
submarines the government needs to get
its act together Navy should get its act
together we need more submarines invest
in submarines quantity is important
quality is also important but quantity
very very
important yeah
so unfortunate if it's true that the
program has been further delayed
whichever program it
is
uh G of jat mum says who do you think
was the best commander of the second
world war roml Eisenhower zukov George
Patton Maur Montgomery you've you've
given me a who's who of of Great War
leaders of great generals roml was
called The Desert Fox wasn't he he did
this brilliant campaign in uh North
Africa but he did not his career did not
end well at all I'll not go into the
details but yeah it was a very bad
ending to his career and he did he did
not deserve that ruml as in
how I would say the greatest commander
of the second world war was Georgie
zukov the guy who defeated the Nazis you
know if you watch Hollywood movies and
all that you will get the feeling that
the Americans defeated the Nazis in the
second world war it's not the case it
was the USSR that defeated the Nazis the
USSR did most of the fighting most of
the dying and most of the
winning and field Marshall George jukov
was instrumental in this so yeah you've
given a number of names of very very
great journals but I would say George
jukov would be my pick for the best
commander of the second world
war okay some more questions do we what
do we
have
um Punjab story says do you think Cyprus
can reunite again Cyprus wants to join
NATO do you think this can escalate War
like same like Russia Ukraine why USA
and UK nowadays so show so much interest
in Cyprus okay let's take the first
question and only that you think Cy
Cyprus can reunite so what's the deal
with Cyprus Cyprus is a partitioned
Nation a divided nation let's go to the
map quickly Google Map here we have it
we go to Cyprus in the Mediterranean Sea
and you can see there are this dashed
lines over here and there's a buffer
zone line of No Control No Man's Land
essentially over here and Northern
Cyprus the northern part above the dash
lines is under occupation by turkey the
southern part is free essentially and
the the people of Cyprus the native
people are of Greek
origin but as a consequence or or or as
a leftover consequence of the otoman
occupation of the region there's a
Turkish population as well they of of
course also have Greek DNA but they are
now Turkish and the Turks have par have
of have occupied the northern part of
the country and the turkey the nation is
partition right now can Cyprus reunite
in the future it's going to be be very
difficult for that to happen I don't see
it happening in the foreseeable future
turkey has its own geopolitical agenda
and plans and
expansionist uh set of Ambitions so I
don't see that happening any time in the
near future or medium-term future maybe
the longterm future you never
know all
right ronu says why me ignored I'm not
sure what you're talking about have you
been asking
questions okay no I'm not sure what you
asked so I don't mean to ignore anybody
but I can only take a limited number of
questions uh Vikram says was Bobby
Fisher the best chess player the world
has ever had probably one of the best I
can't say who is the best but he was
definitely a genuine genius for sure
bobie
Fisher
um right
okay uh what else do we have
Kar alaat says is it really possible to
date ramayan and Mahabharat using
astronomical data it is look you can't
invent
fictitious uh astronomical data if
somebody invents fictitious astronomical
data you can debunk that it's the
simplest thing in the world to debunk
that because the Stars the planets the
constellations Etc they follow Newtonian
mechanics celestian Celestial orbital
Dynamics and all Celestial Dynamics
orbital Dy Dynamics and so on Newtonian
physics it's it's super easy to debunk
any fictitious invented astronomical
data what we know is that the
astronomical data that's encoded in the
ramayan and Mahabharat is not fictitious
it's actual observational
evidence so it should be not very
difficult to determine exactly when in
the past
those positions of various
constellations and other objects
happened the question is the the problem
that we are facing is that various
researchers who are tackling this this
problem their interpretations of the
original Sanskrit text are
different so what they do is they will
take the original Sanskrit text or maybe
a translation to from Sanskrit to Hindi
srit to English and then interpret that
based on that and they all have
different interpretations of what is
written in Sanskrit and that's why they
have different dates that they've thrown
up for the RAM for the
Mahabharat and that's uh the issue so
it's definitely possible to date the
ramayan in the Mahabharat if you can
accurately and correctly interpret what
is written in the original Sanskrit text
otherwise it's going to be a
never-ending fight which we are seeing
every day on social media between these
between these people these researchers
they seem to have this P of fighting
each other in very in a very public way
okay I think we are done with today's
episode with today's live stream 2 hours
13 minutes
plus
so let's take one last question um
maheswar says our reality is based on
SpaceTime fabric whereas in quantum
physics time is a background parameter
why are they both contradictory we don't
know why and that's the big problem that
is one of the big outstanding unsolved
problems or issues in theoretical
physics two of the best theories that we
ever have had in physics quantum
mechanics or Quantum field theory on the
one hand and general relativity general
relativity describes the large scale
struct structure of the universe
brilliantly we have tried to break the
theory it doesn't break it is super
spot-on super
accurate on the other hand in the
microscopic Realm of the universe
quantum theory Quantum field Theory
quantum mechanics absolutely wonderful
Theory works perfectly all the
Technologies we have are based on
quantum physics quantum mechanics
Quantum field Theory but they simply
don't
reconcile in quantum mechanics time is a
external classical parameter yes it's an
external parameter it's a classical
parameter it doesn't emerge from the
theory it comes from
outside and uh in in general relativity
time is one of the four dimensions and
there are issues where you try to
quantize general relativity it doesn't
work it breaks down there are
issues so yeah we don't know why and
that's why we are trying to find a
quantum theory of gravity and we are
thus far failing spectacularly because
string theory was supposedly a solution
it's not worked so it's a work in
progress nobody has the answer to why
this is so and that's what we are trying
to figure out all right with that I
going to end today's session thank you
very much everybody for all your
questions I really appreciate your your
viewership your support and apologies
once again to those whose questions I
could not take obviously there are so
many questions
will continue this next week and I'll
take many more questions then until then
take care keep asking questions keep
raising your standards keep learning and
I'll see you in next week's live stream
bye-bye